Thank you so much for joining us this morning.
If we haven't had the privilege of meeting yet, my name is Ryan, and I have the wonderful
privilege of being one of the pastors here.
And we are continuing a series that we have called A Summer's Journey.
It is summertime, and many of you are going on journeys this summer.
But we are looking at the journeys, the life, the ministry of the Apostle Paul.
And this is the fifth week of this series.
And what I wanted to do really quick before we hop into the meat of the message is I just
wanted to do a recap of where we have been to this point.
I got sick.
We missed an entire message in the life of Paul.
So I'm going to give you that in like 30 seconds.
And then we, you know, we just, we've kind of been flying by.
So I'm going to get you to where we are in his life.
Next week is going to end the biographical kind of overview of Paul's life.
And then we'll dive into some specific kind of theological contributions and just some
of his specific teachings that he gave to the church.
So this is going to be fun.
Here's what's going to happen.
You're going to look at this map.
And then in a minute, we're going to put another map up and you will very quickly be able to
tell which map I made and which map was made by professional map makers.
Okay.
So this is the map that I made.
This is right after.
So remember, Paul, also known as Saul, grew up as a Pharisee in Tarsus, which was a prominent
Roman city.
Saul was a rare Jewish Roman citizen educated in Jerusalem.
And he was zealous for the law of God.
So zealous for the law of God that he ended up persecuting early Christians.
And he was on his way to, does anybody remember the name of the city?
Damascus, he was on his way to Damascus to persecute more Christians.
He had a radical encounter with Jesus.
It changed his perspective about everything.
And this map shows the first 14 years after that incredible encounter with Jesus.
Here's the thing about those 14 years.
We don't know hardly anything about what happened during those 14 years.
There is not much in Scripture about the first 14 years after Paul's encounter with Jesus.
We know for the first three years, he was back and forth between Damascus and Arabia, likely
growing in his faith.
He went to Tarsus, where he's from, for 10 years.
And that's where we practically know nothing about what he did, which is fun.
And then he, Corey talked about Barnabas.
Barnabas grabbed Saul from Tarsus, brought him to Antioch.
And that's really where his leadership in the church began to grow.
So notice that he was a Christian, a follower of Jesus for 14 years before he ever really
had any leadership position.
So that's the first 14 years.
Next, he gets, him and Barnabas get set apart by the Holy Spirit to, we had it.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Next map.
You're right.
Good, good, good.
See, can you tell the difference between my map and the professional map?
Thank you.
That was so nice.
That's the nicest thing anybody's ever said to me.
So Paul and Barnabas get set apart by the Holy Spirit to go on what your Bible titles
will call missionary journeys.
I think Ken's going to talk about this a little bit next week.
I don't love the title missionary journey.
It's not bad.
It's just that some of his, when we think missionary, we think going to people that don't know anything
about the gospel and preaching the gospel to them and trying to get them to become followers
of Jesus.
And although Saul did that some on these journeys, especially the second and third journey were
more what I would call discipleship journeys.
He's taking new believers, new converts in the way of Jesus and forming churches and helping
them to grow in their faith.
So his first journey, him and Barnabas, you can find this in Acts chapter 13 and 14.
It's about a year long journey.
They spent a lot of time at the Galatian church.
So when you read the book of Galatians, he spent a lot of time with the Galatian church
on the first journey.
He was stoned and left for dead.
And he likely wrote the book of Galatians at this time.
Second journey you can find in Acts 15 through 18.
Go back one more.
Sorry.
For two years, him and Barnabas get in a fight, which is fun.
I love this because there's so much humanity in the Scriptures, right?
Like Paul is not perfect.
He is not Jesus.
He is not our Messiah.
We don't know if it was his fault or Barnabas' fault or both of their faults, but our biblical
authors are not perfect human beings.
They get in a fight.
And so Barnabas goes his one way.
And then Paul takes Silas.
And he ends up spending about a year and a half in Corinth during this time.
This is likely when he wrote 1st and 2nd Thessalonians.
Okay.
Next.
This is our last journey.
And this is where the meat of our text is going to be today.
This is his longest journey.
About four years.
You can find it in Acts 18 through 21.
And he spent two whole years, two of his four years, in the city of Ephesus.
He likely wrote 1st and 2nd Corinthians and Romans.
So that's where we are in Saul's life up to this point.
If you're interested in diving deep into the biographical concepts of Paul's life, I will
recommend two very, very different resources.
This one has lots of pictures in it and is easy to read.
And it sticks mostly to the text of Scripture.
It's called The Illustrated Guide to the Apostle Paul.
So if you're a Bible nerd, a history nerd, you want to dive deeper, I'd recommend that.
If you are a history nerd, N.T. Wright is a theologian and church leader.
But he takes his theologian hat off in writing this book.
And he puts a historian hat on.
And so he really just like dives into all of the possibilities of what Paul's life might
have looked like.
So if you're curious, that's a great book.
It's a hard read, unless you're smarter than me, which most of you are.
So, okay.
Does that make sense?
Perfect.
So a couple key takeaways I want to take from Paul's life to this point.
And then we will have, then I'll pray and then we'll get in today's message.
First, if you're in here and you're a follower of Jesus, I hope that you can see from Saul's
life that God has a specific ministry for you, for your life, your upbringing, your circumstances,
all of the things that God has allowed to happen in your life are for a reason.
He has a specific purpose for your life.
And you will find true satisfaction, true fulfillment when you find that purpose and live into it.
Wow, that was better than you guys responded.
Okay.
God has a purpose for your life.
Live into it.
If you're in here, you're not a follower of Jesus, just like Saul.
I believe God wants to have a radical encounter with you.
He wants you to have a radical encounter with him that will change the trajectory of your life
and your eternity.
Sound good?
And then lastly, if you're in here and you are, let's say, older than 65, I'm just drawing a random line in the sand.
Notice that up to this point in Paul's life, we have covered everything except for the last 10 years of his life.
And we have less than half of his biblical contributions.
So what I want to say here is, if you're an older person in the room, we only have 10 years of Paul's life left to cover at this point.
And he has written less than half of his biblical contributions.
You still have so much to add to the value.
You have so much value to add to the kingdom of God.
I love what Eugene Peterson says.
Remember where we are in Paul's life in Acts chapter 20.
He was near the end with a lot of adventure and accomplishment behind him.
But instead of sitting back, he set sail.
And in doing so, he set an example for all of us.
Is that beautiful?
Scott, there's like lots of noise going on back, like right behind stage.
Do you mind just checking that out for me?
I'm sorry.
So distracted.
All right, let's pray while Scott goes and make sure I'm safe.
Thank you, Scott.
Father in heaven, we are so grateful for this opportunity to continue diving into learning about the life of Paul.
Thank you for his example.
Thank you for the fact that he is just like we are human.
And yet, he submitted himself to the Holy Spirit and was used by you to do incredible things for your glory.
And so, God, may we learn from that life and ministry.
May we grow in our faith.
It's in Jesus' name I pray.
Amen.
If you want to follow along in your Bibles, we're going to be in Acts chapter 20.
I am in Luke chapter 20, which is why it did not look right.
All right.
Acts chapter 20, starting in verse 17.
I'd love for you to raise your hand.
Do me a favor.
How many of you are big picture takers?
Like you take too many pictures when you go on family trips or when you're just in your living room.
Okay, we've got some people pointing at each other, which is great.
I'm a big picture taker, and what happens often is, like, I take 57 of the same pictures.
Does anybody else do this?
Okay, good.
I'm not alone.
So, I'll take 57 of the same pictures, and then my Apple iCloud will be full.
And I will have to go back and realize that I have 57 of the same pictures and delete.
Usually 50 of them.
I usually keep seven or so, even though they are all still the same, because I have, like, a hoarding problem with my pictures.
But what happens if you're, like, anything like me, you go back and you look at that, like, big chunk of pictures in your photo library, and they're almost all identical, right?
They have some nuances and some differences, but at the end of the day, you could really just have one of those pictures, and it will give you a gist of, like, the whole thing that was happening, right?
So, I bring that up because Saul went on lots of trips, three big journeys.
He was in all kinds of different cities, doing all kinds of different things.
And Luke, in the book of Acts, he doesn't give us all of them.
He actually gives us very few of them.
He spends, a lot of times, he'll be like, he went there, he went there, he went there, he went there, and he doesn't tell you anything that happened in those places that he went.
Does that make sense?
But when he ends, at the very end of Saul's third journey, which is where we're at in Acts chapter 20, Luke zooms in on this encounter where Paul is interacting with the leaders of the Ephesian church.
And I think what Luke intentionally uses this story, it's like the picture, it's the summary of all the things that often happened with Saul as he was in different cities and doing different ministry with different places.
It's like the photo that gives us the understanding of all the other photos.
Does that make sense?
Okay, so I thought it was really important that we zoom in on this story in Paul's life, because I think it gives us a snapshot of what his ministry, what his message, what his values are throughout his three journeys.
That if we look at the Ephesian church, we can see all of the things that Paul was about for the last 10 years of his three journeys that we just looked at.
That sound good?
Cool.
All right, stand up with me.
We're going to read the whole story, and then we're going to dive into some specifics.
What I want you to look for as we read the whole story is he's going to start with his testimony of how he ministered in the city of Ephesus.
He's going to talk about kind of his methods for ministry, his message for ministry, and his values, and then he's going to give them some warnings about what they can expect as he leaves them and lets them take leadership.
So just pay attention.
Got it?
Cool.
All right.
Now for my leadus, Paul sent to Ephesus and called the elders, the leadership of the church, to come to him.
And when they came to him, this is what he said.
You yourselves know how I have lived among you the whole time from the first day that I set foot in Asia, serving the Lord with all humility, with tears, and with trials that happened to me through the plots of the Jews.
How I did not shrink from declaring to you anything that was profitable and teaching you in public and from house to house, testifying both to the Jews and to the Greeks of repentance towards God and of faith in our Lord Jesus.
And now behold, I am going to Jerusalem, constrained by the Spirit, not knowing what will happen to me there, except that the Holy Spirit testifies to me in every city that imprisonment and inflictions await me.
But I do not account my life of any value, nor as precious to myself, if only I may finish my course in the ministry that I have received from the Lord Jesus, to testify to the gospel of the grace of God.
And now behold, I know that none of you whom I have gone about proclaiming the kingdom of God will see my face again.
Therefore, I testify to you this day that I am innocent of your blood.
For I did not shrink back from declaring to you the whole counsel of God.
Now, pay careful attention to yourselves and to all of the flock in which the Holy Spirit has made you overseers, to care for the church of God, which he obtained with his own blood.
I know that after my departure, fierce wolves will come in among you, not sparing the flock, and from among your own selves will arise men speaking twisted things to draw away the disciples after them.
Therefore, be alert, remembering that for three years I did not cease night or day to admonish everyone with tears.
And now I commend you to God and to the word by his grace, which is able to build you up and to give you the inheritance among all those who are sanctified.
This is the part you don't have to listen to, okay?
I'm just kidding.
I'm kidding.
I coveted no one silver or gold.
You yourselves know that these hands ministered to my necessities and to those who are with me.
Paul did all of his ministry in Ephesus for free.
Don't get any ideas.
Okay.
And all the things I have shown you that by working hard in this way, we must help the weak and remember the words of the Lord Jesus, how he himself said, it is more blessed to receive.
He said all of these things.
He knelt down and prayed with them, and there was much weeping on the part of all of them.
They embraced Paul, and they kissed him, being sorrowful most of all because of the word that he had spoken, that they would not see his face again.
And they accompanied him to the ship.
You can sit down.
So, Paul had spent about two years of his life doing ministry in the city of Ephesus.
He had great affection for these people.
He calls their leadership to him, knowing that he will likely not ever be in Ephesus again or see their faces.
He wants to give them a final reminder of how to lead the church, and he starts by giving them a testimony of how he started the church, of what he did in leading the church.
He gives a brief description of what his ministry was like in Ephesus, which I think is a good summary of what most of his ministry was like in a lot of the cities.
As you read the book of Exodus, you get this pattern that Saul or Paul led with throughout his visits to the cities.
This is what it looks like.
He would go to the synagogue, the Jewish temple, the Jewish gathering space on Sabbath, and he would begin to proclaim the message of the gospel.
What would happen in the synagogue is that some Jews and some what the Bible calls God-fearers, which is just Greeks who would go to church in the synagogue because they were interested in the things of Yahweh.
Some Jews, some God-fearers, would accept the gospel of Jesus with gladness.
Many Jews would get furious.
They would run Saul out of the synagogue or Paul, and they wouldn't want anything to do with him.
And so then he would turn to the Gentiles.
He would go to a secular meeting space, and he would proclaim the same message, that the resurrected Jesus is Israel's Messiah, that everything has changed, the way in which we live, our lives should change.
Some Gentiles would receive that message.
Others would get furious.
Then what would happen sometimes is the Jews and the Gentiles who were furious, they would kind of come together and run Saul out of town or try and kill him.
And this happened over and over and over again.
And Saul would work with the people who had received the message with gladness, and he would start a church.
He would raise up leaders, and he would encourage them to be faithful to the message of the gospel, to keep sharing that message, and he would go on to the next city.
Does that make sense?
Okay, so that had happened with Saul in Ephesus.
He'd spent a long time there, and he is telling them, look, this is what happened to me in your city.
Look in verse 19.
He said, I served you with all humility and with tears and with trials that happened to me through the plots of the Jews.
He said, I did everything I could to preach the message faithfully, and yet I got persecuted.
He got persecuted by the Jews.
He got persecuted by the Gentiles.
Everywhere he went, he got persecuted.
Now, why is it that he got persecuted by both Jews and Gentiles?
Well, in verse 20, no, 21, he summarizes his message, and the message that he is sharing is the reason why he offends so many Jews and so many Gentiles all throughout his ministry.
Remember I said that this is like a snapshot of everything that he did in all of the cities?
This sentence right here in verse 21, this is a summary.
Although Paul preached lots of other things, if you want to know the gist, the one sentence, thesis statement of Paul's message that he preached in all of his cities, that everywhere he went, this is what he preached.
This is the message that Paul preached that made many Jews and many Gentiles try and kill him over and over and over again from city to city to city.
To the Jews and to the Greeks, I proclaimed repentance towards God and faith in the Lord Jesus.
This is the message.
Does this sound familiar to any of us?
Does this sound like the gospel that we've heard preached from time to time?
There's some similarities there.
There's some familiarity there.
But here's what happens.
I think in the American church, this seemingly simple statement, we've become way too familiar with it.
It's just the thing that we've heard growing up over and over again.
It's the thing that we sing in our songs.
It's the phrase that we say and we repeat and we agree with.
And yet I think we lose sight of what it actually means.
We lose sight of the implications that it has on our lives.
And we lose sight of how in the world this simple, basic message could have flipped the entire world upside down in the first century.
Over and over again, from city to city to city, people heard this message and they were either offended and tried to persecute Paul and his crew or they submitted their entire lives to it.
This isn't some generic spiritual statement that we just sing in a song or tack on to the end of a prayer.
This message that Paul is preaching has incredible implications for our lives to the Jews and the Greeks.
The first thing that's offensive about that is he's preaching the same message of salvation to both of these groups of people.
And the Jews are like, no, no, no, no, no.
We're God's people.
We're special.
This message is for us first.
Maybe they can have it later.
But right now it's for us.
And Saul says, no, it's for both of you.
And this is the message.
First, repentance.
All of us who have grown up in church know that repentance means to change your mind, right?
To change your mind.
But he adds a clarifier here.
Towards God.
Change your mind and go in the right direction.
Repentance towards God.
And then faith, which Michelle did a really good job of covering last week, is way more than just intellectual belief.
Remember she said that the demons believe?
Faith is so much more than just intellectual belief.
It is a strong conviction.
Sometimes it carries the weight of fidelity or loyalty.
Caesar would actually proclaim to his people, Caesar is Lord.
Place your faith, your pistis in me as Lord.
It was a political statement of authority.
And Paul is saying, no, no one but Jesus is Lord.
You place your allegiance, your faith, your trust in him.
Now, with that little bit unpacked, can we begin to see how it might have been offensive to some?
It's not just a generic spiritual phrase.
It is a declaration of where the direction of your life is headed.
Of who are you submitting to?
Where is your authority being placed?
Saul says, if you want to follow Jesus, you place your allegiance in him as Lord, master, owner, the one who gets to call the shots.
This is not a neutered spiritual word that we sing, but a powerful and practical and even political world.
Every other authority figure takes the back seat to Jesus if you want to follow him.
So, this message can become a little bit offensive to some.
I want to unpack how in which the Jews and the Gentiles were offended in different ways.
Because they were offended in different ways.
First, the Jews.
The Jews had a religious nature, a prideful nature.
So, the first reason the Jews were offended was because of their pride.
They had been set apart as God's people for thousands of years.
And they forgot that their whole reason God set them apart was so that they could be a blessing to the rest of the world.
Right?
This is what God tells Abraham.
I'm going to bless you.
I'm going to create a nation through you.
And through that nation, you will bless the rest of the world.
But they'd lost sight of that promise.
And they were prideful about their way of salvation.
And when Paul came and proclaimed the same message of salvation to the Jews and to the Greeks,
all you have to do is repent.
Change your mind towards God and place your faith and trust in Jesus.
The Jews were like, no.
They have to get circumcised and they have to obey the Mosaic law.
Paul's like, no, if that happened, if that's how they would receive the message of salvation,
then nothing has changed.
Because there was a way in which Gentiles could receive salvation in the Old Testament.
It was by getting circumcised and obeying all the Mosaic laws.
And the Jews are like, yeah, exactly.
If they want to be a part of us, they have to do all the things that we're doing.
And this is what Paul would say to that.
He says, in his writing to the Galatians, he says,
if righteousness comes through the law, then Christ died for no purpose.
So he's telling the Jews, no.
If they're just receiving the message of salvation through circumcision and obedience to the law,
then why did God even send Jesus?
What's the whole point of this whole thing?
So the Jews are offended with pride.
And I think more importantly, and I think this is the one that has more of an application to the American church,
is the Jews were very afraid at this time.
This was a very volatile time in the Roman Empire.
And the Jews had a really, they had a unique exemption with the Roman government
that allowed them not to worship any of the other Roman gods.
They were the religion, the nation that was allowed to just worship their God.
And now this new group of people, these new Christians, they are saying,
wait a second, we also only have one God.
We are not going to worship the Roman gods.
And now the Romans have a problem and the Jews have a problem.
Okay?
Because there was so much going on in this culture.
And the Romans were already kind of regretting their decision to let the Jews not worship the Roman gods.
And now there's a new group that's saying, we're not with them, but we also don't want to worship your gods.
Now there was some really loaded political ramifications there.
And so the Jews were reacting out of fear because they were like, look, if this group continues to grow,
then the Romans are going to cut us all off.
They're going to persecute us.
They're not going to let us worship God.
They're not going to let us come to the temple.
They're not going to let us do our sacrificial systems.
And guess what happened?
All of that, all of these fears happened around 70 AD, right?
Like this stuff happened.
The Jews had a good idea of what was going to happen if these Christians kept growing,
kept becoming more and more important.
And I think, I think this temptation, this fear, this reason that we can tend to drift away from obedience to the gospel
is still true of Christians in America today.
See, Christians in America, we've had a unique position of influence and power in our culture throughout the history of our nation.
Can we agree with that?
And as the culture rejects Christian ideas more and more, I see so many Christians, listen to this, this is so important.
I see so many Christians responding out of, responding in anger fueled by fear.
We get angry, we yell, we yell, we scream, we throw stones.
Why do we do it?
We do it because we're afraid.
We're afraid as the nation becomes less and less Christian, as the nation becomes more and more anti-Christian,
we're worried that our comfort is going to go away.
Our influence is going to go away.
Our power is going to go away.
And we've become more worried about our comfort than our testimony.
We need to remember this, church, that Jesus will build his church.
And the gates of hell will not prevail against it.
But listen to me, listen to me, listen to me.
He does not need us to be influential in our culture in order for him to build his church.
That's like upside down from all of our businesses and political ideologies.
Like in America, what do you need in order to be, to make a difference?
You need influence.
You need power.
The kingdom of God is upside down from that.
Jesus does not need us to be influential or powerful in order to make a difference in our community.
Here's the reality is that the church actually grows way more throughout history
when they're being persecuted and pushed to the margins.
Do you know why?
Because when the church is persecuted and pushed to the margins, guess who doesn't come to church anymore?
The Christians that don't actually believe that Jesus is Lord and gets to call the shots in their life.
And so, I think, like the Jews, the American church has become fearful of losing our influence.
We try and grasp at it through our democracy, through who we vote for, through our social media influence.
And I'm just like, I'm stepping back and looking at even Christian leaders on social media.
And we're just so fearful that we're going to lose power and control.
And I'm just not sold that us losing power and control isn't actually good for the health of the church
and our influence and our country moving forward.
Jesus doesn't need us to be influential.
He needs us to be obedient.
And the church actually tends to flourish way more when it's persecuted
and pushed outside the positions of culture and political influence.
Are we willing to repent, to change our ideas about how God can work in our culture?
Are we willing to submit to Jesus as Lord and realize that he might be having the most impact
through us laying down our privileges and our power in order to serve those on the margins?
All right.
So, that's how the Jews were offended by Paul's message to repent, to turn towards God,
to place your faith and trust in Jesus alone as Lord and master of your life.
And this is why the Gentiles got offended.
Do I have time for that?
No, let's skip that one.
All right.
Idolatry, right?
So, the Gentiles, they loved the gods.
They were usually really open-minded to adding more and more gods to their menu of gods.
And so, here's the thing that made Paul's message, the gospel of Jesus, so offensive to the Gentiles
because Paul did not say Jesus is a Son of God that demands your worship.
If Paul would have said Jesus is a Son of God that demands your worship,
the Gentiles would have been like, sounds great.
Where do we put his statue?
What kind of sacrifice does he want?
What kind of incense does he want us to burn?
Give us the rules.
Tell us the things and we'll do it.
But that's not the message.
The message is Jesus alone is the Lord, the master, the Son of God.
And if you want to follow him, you have to get rid of all of your other gods.
You have to place your faith, your trust, your allegiance in him alone.
Not only do you have to get rid of all other gods,
you've got to get rid of Rome as the supreme authority and leader of your life.
Jesus has to be the supreme authority of your life.
And does that now make sense why some Gentiles would be offended by that?
Idolatry.
The Gentiles loved the gods.
And they would have added Jesus willingly as long as he didn't demand supreme loyalty.
Now, do we see where I'm going with this?
Many secular people in our nation today still respond this way to Jesus.
They're fine with Jesus plus whatever other things they've got going on in their life.
Many of us in the church today are fine with Jesus plus whatever other things that we have going on in our life,
whatever ideologies, political beliefs, whatever it is.
So many of us are great with Jesus plus.
The problem with that is Paul's message is not Jesus plus, it's Jesus alone.
A lot of Americans are willing to embrace Jesus as a significant part of their lives,
but it's offensive and oppressive to suggest that Jesus is the way, the truth, and the life.
Many of us are willing to add Jesus to our worldview as long as it means Jesus plus.
I'll give some examples just so that you know where I'm headed and we can be all offended equally.
Jesus plus nationalism.
Jesus plus progressivism.
Jesus plus individualism.
As long as I get to hold on to the thing that I like most about being American,
the thing that I like most that makes me most comfortable,
as long as Jesus doesn't tell me that some of those things aren't true.
And here's the thing where it gets slippery is all of those ideologies have glimpses of truth,
and so we embrace the part of Jesus that affirms those things,
and we ignore the part of Jesus that calls us for our own idolatry and rebellion.
And if we want to actually follow Jesus, we've got to allow him to call us on the false beliefs and ideologies that we're holding on to.
We love the Jesus that believes everything that we believe.
I love the Jesus that believes everything that I believe,
which is why a diverse community of believers is so important,
because I need people who think differently than me and love me and love Jesus to say,
dude, you've got some blind spots over here.
We all need each other because all of us have blind spots.
And we're really good at just listening to the voice of Jesus that agrees with everything that we're already doing and thinking and believing.
Paul's gospel is offensive to the proud and fearful religious as well as a sophisticated and open-minded secularist,
but it is life.
It is life to those of us who are willing to receive it with humility,
to lay down our old ideologies and lifestyles,
and to embrace Jesus as the supreme Lord and leader of our life.
I love how Paul puts it in 1 Corinthians.
For the Jews demand signs,
the Greeks seek wisdom,
but we preach Christ crucified,
a stumbling block to the Jews and folly to the Gentiles,
but to those of us who are called,
both Jews and Greeks,
Christ is the power and the wisdom of God.
Paul's saying it's foolish,
it's offensive to religious Jews who are fearful and trying to hold on to power.
It's offensive to secular Gentiles who are just,
they want wisdom,
they want it to all make sense,
they want it to all add up.
Paul says it doesn't all add up.
The gospel demands the response of us laying down our life.
It doesn't make sense to the culture,
but it is truth and will lead to life.
Paul then,
that's his message,
why it's offensive.
Oh,
I'm going way too far,
way too fast.
Sorry.
He then goes on to,
to just double down on why all of this matters.
He shares his value system,
his value structure.
Verse 24,
I do not count my life of any value,
nor as precious to myself,
if only I may finish my course in the ministry that I have received from the Lord Jesus,
to testify to the gospel of the grace of our God.
Saying,
look,
I'm cool with being persecuted.
I'm cool with being thrown out of cities.
I'm cool with being stoned and left for dead,
because this life,
this temporary earthly life is not all that matters.
There is an eternity that is coming that my hope is in,
and I am okay with suffering and being persecuted.
I'm okay with being laughed at,
rejected,
and mocked,
because my life is not invested in just here and now.
My life is invested in eternity.
This is Paul's value system.
This is what drives Paul's decision-making.
The gospel that,
that the gospel of Jesus that Paul preaches,
emphasizes the importance of eternal value over any earthly or temporary gain.
Because of the hope of the resurrection.
Look,
we see this in Paul's own response to the gospel.
Before Paul submitted his life to Jesus,
he was a man of power and influence.
He was a religious leader that got all kinds of praise from all kinds of people.
And he said,
you know what?
All of that was worthless.
Later,
he'll call it rubbish,
garbage.
None of it matters in light of the eternal hope of the resurrection of Jesus.
The reason that Paul is okay with being,
with offending people and being rejected with tears and with pain is because all of it is
an investment in the eternal hope of Jesus.
All right.
So that's Paul's summary of how he did ministry,
why he did ministry,
what he said,
how it offended all of the people that he interacted with.
Now,
he's going to look the leaders of the Ephesian church in the eye,
and he's going to give them a warning.
He says,
look,
I've done everything I could do.
I have to leave now.
And you guys are in charge.
So this is his final warning to the leaders of the Ephesian church.
Verse 25.
He says,
And now behold,
I know that none of you among whom I have gone about proclaiming the kingdom of God will ever see my face again.
Therefore,
I testify to you this day that I am innocent of the blood.
I've told you everything that I can tell you,
how you respond to it is of utmost importance.
I did not shrink back from declaring to you the whole counsel of God.
Therefore,
pay careful attention to yourselves and to all the flock,
which the Holy Spirit has made you overseers,
to care for the church of God,
which is obtained by his own blood.
I know that after my departure,
fierce wolves will come in among you,
not sparing the flock.
And from among your own selves will arise men speaking twisted things to draw away the disciples after them.
Therefore,
be alert.
All right.
So,
I am.
We've got to go fast.
You guys put your seatbelts on for me?
All right.
So,
he gives some,
he gives some exhortations and some warnings.
First,
his exhortations.
He tells the leaders that he has taught them everything they need to know and what they need to do with that information is ultimately on them.
And the first,
the top priority that he gives to them is he says,
pay attention to yourselves,
to your own lives.
The top priority for Paul,
if the church is going to be healthy and successful moving forward,
if the Ephesian church is going to last persecution,
last difficulty,
last challenges,
the first thing that has to happen is the leaders of the church have to prioritize personal faithfulness.
They have to be holy.
They have to be obedient to the teachings of Scripture.
Does this sound like it might be a priority that the American church might need to embrace?
See,
it's very easy for church leaders to get so focused on the tasks of ministry.
And this is the part of the sermon that I'm going to preach to myself and the few leaders in the room.
I think it has implications for the rest of us,
but I'm just going to call myself out for a minute and then we'll get back to you.
All right.
It's very easy for church leaders to get so focused on the tasks of ministry that we neglect our relationship with and obedience to God.
We use the fruit of our ministry to justify our lack of character and it's killing the church.
Just this week,
as I was preparing the sermon this week,
another very well-known church leader.
It came out that he had hidden sin in his life from years and years ago.
It finally came out.
People are leaving the church in droves because of the hypocrisy of Christian leaders.
And Paul says,
if you want to be successful,
if you want the fruit of your ministry to last,
leaders,
you've got to pay attention to your life,
to your obedience,
to your faithfulness,
to your holiness.
You can't get so consumed with ministry that you forget about your relationship with God.
We shouldn't expect perfection from our leaders,
but we should expect honesty,
confession,
and accountability.
But because we've allowed our leaders to elevate their title to an identity and their paycheck as necessity,
it often encourages cover-ups and justifications.
This is like a message to a pastor's conference,
so I'll move on quickly.
All right.
But this happens.
Carl Vader says this.
He says,
integrity is the new competency.
Integrity is the new competency.
If the church wants people from the outside to look at us and to give us a voice in our life,
the most important thing is that we have integrity.
See,
the generation before us,
before me,
I don't know why I did that to all of you.
The generation before me,
competency was so important,
right?
Like businesses were growing,
expanding,
booming.
What we needed from our leaders is that they knew how to lead.
But guess where that led us?
We had a lot of really good leaders with no character,
no morality.
And now my generation is looking at that and saying,
look,
we don't care if you're a good leader or not.
Are you genuine?
Are you authentic?
Are you honest?
So this is what we need from our church leaders.
We need integrity.
He tells Paul,
not only do you have to look out for your life,
but you have to look out for the life of the rest of the flock.
Pay careful attention to yourselves and to all the flock in which the Holy Spirit made you overseers.
Not only is faithful obedience a top priority of church leaders,
but it's a top priority for all of you sitting in this room that would consider yourself a follower of Jesus.
We need to become,
listen to this.
This is,
I'm going to go on a rant real quick.
We need to become less obsessed with getting our theology perfect and more obsessed with getting our obedience on track.
Notice the first thing that Paul says to the church and to the leaders is not make sure your doctrine is perfect.
The first thing that he says is make sure that you keep track of your obedience.
And we get this flip-flop in the American church.
Guess what he's going to say next?
Spoiler alert.
He's going to say doctrine is important,
but it's secondary to obedience.
We need to become less obsessed with getting our theology perfect and more obsessed with getting our obedience on track.
Because the church of Jesus is the most valuable asset of the kingdom of God on earth.
He says it's been bought with the precious blood of Jesus.
And what Jesus wants for his church is obedience.
And what Jesus wants for his church is obedience, is submission, is faith.
Nothing will render us less effective than if we neglect faithful obedience to the teachings and examples of Jesus.
You guys have heard me talk about golf on stage.
I won't bore you to death.
But any of you that golf know that golf is a very hard sport.
And almost nobody that I golf with, almost nobody in this room who golf knows anything about golf.
It's so hard.
It's so technical.
And you know what is infuriating as a golfer is to stand up on the tee, make a bad shot, and then have the person behind you tell you what you did wrong.
When you and they both know that you all stink at golf.
So it's like, you're going to tell me how to golf, right?
And this is what we have going on in the church, is we have a bunch of people in the church pointing fingers at the culture outside of our walls, telling them how they should live when we aren't taking our own advice.
We need to prioritize obedience and faithfulness over good doctrine instead.
But what we like to do is we like to just have all the right answers on a checklist that we ignore and say, well, because we know all the right answers, you guys should listen to us.
And they're like, you guys aren't even following your own instructions.
Listen to this.
Evangelist Rodney Smith says, there are five Gospels.
Matthew, Mark, Luke, John, and the Christian life, and most people won't read the first four.
And so Paul says, the top priority for the church's success moving forward is that we live out and obey the teachings of Jesus.
Because our life is the testimony of what Jesus is like to a watching world.
Okay?
And then he moves on.
He doesn't say doctrine doesn't matter at all.
He says, look, there are going to be false teachers who are going to come in, and they're going to try and distort you.
They're going to try and lead you astray.
Verse 29.
I'm almost done, I promise.
I know that after my departure, fierce wolves will come in from among you, not sparing the flock.
And from among your own selves will arise men speaking twisted things to draw people away after them.
Therefore, be alert, remembering that for three years I did not cease day or night to admonish everyone with tears.
So he says, look, false teachers are going to come in.
They're going to come in both from inside and from outside the church, and they're going to try and draw the church away from obedience to the true message of the gospel.
Good doctrine is important, but it cannot come before obedience.
And I think the American church is particularly susceptible to this temptation.
We have so much access to receive and to communicate information that we'd rather study nuanced doctrine and fight with other Christians online than to love our neighbors and to sacrificially serve the needy and vulnerable in our community.
Look, I want discipleship at our church to prioritize, to emphasize obedience as much, if not more, than education.
But the American church for years and years and years has said, if you want to be discipled, if you want to learn about your faith, it's all about information.
And we've neglected application.
And here's the sad news.
The sad news is that the Ephesian elders that Paul is warning right now, they fell trapped to that very same thing.
Forty years later, John writes the book of Revelation that we all, everybody in here's favorite book, right?
Okay.
John writes the book of Revelation.
He gives the Ephesian church a message directly from Jesus to them.
And I'm going to summarize it for you.
This is the message that Jesus gives the Ephesian church.
He says, you guys can spot a false teacher from a mile away.
But you have lost your first love.
Isn't that sad?
Paul's warning to them, first, take care of your relationship with God.
Take care of your holiness.
Take care of your obedience.
Prioritize it.
Make it an important reality in your life.
And then be careful that people don't come in and try and lead you astray with false teaching.
They overemphasize the false teaching part, forgot to emphasize the relationship part.
And Jesus warns them.
He says, look, you guys are great at doctrine.
You know the Bible inside and out, but you do not love each other and you do not love your neighbor.
May this be a warning to us.
It's really hard to get all of this right.
Right?
Which is why we need to rely on Jesus and the Holy Spirit and one another.
All right, notice there's false teachers inside and outside the church.
It's important for us to pursue intentional reliance on the Holy Spirit, a good understanding of the Scriptures,
so that we can spot false teachers inside the church, but also outside the church.
Paul says this to Timothy in 2 Timothy 4.
He says,
For the time is coming when people will not endure sound teaching, but having itching ears,
they will accumulate for themselves teachers to suit their own passions.
Be careful, if you're in here, not to become the type of Christian that just looks for teachers that will tell you what you want to hear.
Don't find a Bible teacher who will just tell you the version of Jesus that already fits your own ideology and your preferences and your lifestyle.
On the other side of the coin,
don't just find the meanest, grumpiest Bible teacher you've ever found in your life and say,
Well, he must be the only one preaching truth.
Both of these groups can generate a crowd, right?
You've got this more secular, progressive Bible teacher that will water down holiness and obedience and will just present a Jesus that all of us can embrace and won't call any of us on our sin.
We've seen that?
Okay.
And on the other side, you have mean, grumpy fundamentalists who water, who like shrink down, make doctrine the only important thing.
They don't represent the love of Jesus at all.
And they say, we're the only ones who are preaching truth.
And the reason nobody likes us is because this, right?
We're the only ones preaching truth.
No, nobody likes you because you're mean.
All right.
So, be careful not to go to either pendulum.
The life and teachings of Jesus is the ultimate litmus test for sound doctrine.
And many people on both sides will emphasize some parts of his life and some parts of his teaching that fit their agenda,
but they'll miss the whole thing.
All right.
I have way more to say, and I don't have time to say it.
Let me end here.
All right.
Let's go to verse 36.
I want one last application point that we will likely have to come back to as a church if we continue to grow.
And that is this, the hard necessity of gospel goodbyes.
At the end of Paul's speech, at the end of his warnings, this is what we read in verse 36.
After he said these things, he knelt down and he prayed with them all.
And there was much weeping on the part of all of them.
They embraced Paul and they kissed him, being sorrowful.
Most of all, because of the word that he'd spoken, that they would not see his face again.
So, there's this emotional goodbye.
They're not going to see each other anymore.
And the application I would say to this is that Paul and the Ephesian leaders seem to be very fond of one another.
They would likely prefer to just continue doing ministry together in Ephesus.
But the importance of the proclamation of the gospel and the prompting of the Holy Spirit in Paul's life required him to separate with them.
And if our church continues to grow, we will likely have to send some people out to plant or revitalize struggling churches.
And if it were up to me, listen, once we get full, I'd close our doors and we'd hang out for the rest of our time together until I die or until Jesus returns.
Because I really like you guys.
I do.
It's crazy.
But our community needs more healthy churches who will proclaim the gospel and make disciples.
And if that need requires us to split or to multiply, I want us to consider that task of making disciples more important than our own personal preferences.
Because the church that is more interested in their preferences over the mission of the kingdom of God will die in a generation.
And the church was purchased with the very blood of Jesus.
And so if that's how we're going to steward his church, I don't want to be a part of it.
All right.
I got to go.
I'm so sorry.
Let's pray.
Father, I thank you for this incredibly dense text that I fumbled our way through this morning.
I pray that the Holy Spirit would bring it to light in all of our minds and our hearts.
May we revisit it this week and learn from it.
May we learn from the warnings that Paul gives the leaders of the Ephesian church.
May we prioritize obedience.
May we prioritize our relationship with you over and above being doctrinally perfect.
May we also refuse to be led astray by false teachers.
God, conform your church into your image.
Make us a faithful and obedient church for your glory and our good and the good of our neighbor.
It's in Jesus' name I pray.
Amen.
Okay.
So we're getting ready to transition to communion in just a second.
First, we're going to play a song for Father's Day.
So I selected this song on purpose.
And if you're on live stream, we're not going to be able to play it for you because that would be breaking the law.
And what did I just say about the church being obedient, right?
All right.
So I picked this song.
It's called Dad's Song.
And the reason I picked it is because I think it is a holistic response to Father's Day and to the emotion that Father's Day might bring to a room this big and this diverse.
It is a song written from the perspective of God to us as his children.
And here's where I think it applies and has implications for our lives.
First and foremost, those of us who are in here who are dads, it is a reminder that we have a perfect example of a heavenly father.
That we are going to fall short, that we are not going to be a perfect dad.
And yet when we fail, when we fall short, we have a perfect heavenly father who will forgive us and give us grace.
And for those of us in here who have a difficult, challenging, broken relationship with our father,
it's a reminder that no matter what our earthly relationship with our father might look like, we have a perfect heavenly father.
It was not his will or his desire that we would have a broken relationship.
And he comes in and provides that restoration and that healing.
So let's check it out and then I'll come back and lead us in communion.
Thank you.
All right.
We should have a map, I think, that tells us how this works.
And if not, we're in trouble because there's no way I'm going to remember how it goes.
Here we go.
So in just a minute, I'm going to dismiss you to come get your elements and then just keep on to them and we will take them together.
If you're new or newer to Canvas, we practice what we call open communion, which means we believe that the Lord's Supper is for all believers.
So you don't have to be in communion.
So you don't have to be a member of our church to partake, but we're counting on you to police yourself.
If you've never made the decision to follow Jesus as the Lord and leader of your life, communion is something that is not for you.
And that is not meant to be offensive or keeping you out.
It's an invitation that you can come to and receive anytime.
But until you're willing to submit your life to his lordship, to his leadership, it's something that we ask for you not to partake in.
And nobody is going to stare at you or be weirded out by you staying in your seat.
And if they are, tell me and I'll have a conversation with them.
All right.
So, cool.
Come grab your stuff and I will be back in just a minute to lead us through it.
Do the instructions make sense?
I did not.
Good luck.
Godspeed.
I don't know that we have.
I have to turn this one up.
I don't know that we have to turn this one up.
All right.
Well, communion is intended to help us to remember.
To remember the beauty of the message of the gospel.
To remember the response that the message of the gospel demands in our lives.
And what a good summary of the communion elements, the communion passage, in our passage in Acts
this morning where Paul says that the church was purchased with a broken body and shed blood
of Jesus.
That's why obedience matters.
That's why doctrine matters.
All of it matters because the church was purchased by the blood of Jesus.
So if you're in here and you're a follower of Jesus, I'd invite you to take the bread, which
is a representation of Christ's body broken for you.
Drink the juice.
It's a representation of Christ's blood shed for you.